This week we're going to look at making
Ben and Jerry's fudgy flan flavor. Man,
that's a lot of Fs.
So, first off, we need to talk about
flan. Now, to me, as an old far English
man, flan is something different. Flan
is kind of like a kiche, if you will.
Um, but in Europe we call flan creme
caramel, which is a fancy French
dessert. It's not fancy at all. It's
like a baked custard with a semi burnt
caramel drizzled over the top. And it's
baked upside down. So you put the
caramel in, the burnt caramel in the
bottom, then you set that in the
refrigerator for a few minutes. Then you
put your custard over the top, and then
you bake it. Then when you turn it out,
it's all like that. Exactly the same as
flam. Now, Flan is a South American
thing. So, Spanish-sp speakaking regions
of South America, that's what they call
flan. It has pretty good reviews to be
fair, but they all say the same thing
and that is the creme peticier.
So, pastry cream if you will. It is
totally missing out the tubs. And I can
tell you why that happens. And that is
if you make cremepoticier, I don't know
whether to say it the fancy way like
that or pastry cream. Maybe I'll just
mix and match. If you make that with the
moment you put it in the freezer, it
will split as it starts to defrost. And
that's just the nature of how it's made.
The the balance of the ingredients means
it will start to separate as it moves
out of its frozen state into a
semifrozen state and it will just
disappear into the ice cream. So maybe
that's what they're doing. But, you
know, we also know that Ben & Jerry's
literally don't give a as to what
they put in the tubs. They say one thing
on the tub and what you get inside is
often like totally different. You know,
addins missing, none of this, loads of
that. Now that you can make it at home,
you're kind of in control as to what you
do to it. So, that's what we're going to
do today. Um, how do they describe it?
Ben and Jerry's describe fudgy flan as a
burnt caramel ice cream with fudge
brownies and pastry cream swirls. So,
sounds really good. Let's get on and
make it. What are we going to need for
the ice cream base? We're going to
change it up slightly. We're going to
keep the base the same. Burnt caramel
base. We're going to do brownie add-ins.
I'm not going to make brownies from
scratch this time. I'm going to use a
packet mix brownie. You can use two by
brownies from Costco. They're excellent
ice cream if you're interested. Uh, and
that's because they're loaded in sugar,
so they don't freeze super hard. Um, but
the pastry cream swell, we're going to
do a slightly different take on that.
We're going to do a modified pastry
cream crimpier
um so it doesn't split. So for the ice
cream base for fudgy fl you are going to
need 330 g of whipping cream or higher
454 g of whole milk which is 3.25% here.
30 g of burnt caramel which is burnt in
a pan with a touch of water but we'll go
through that a bit later. 112 g of
sugar. 1.5 g of go 4 g less less thanin
35 g of skim milk powder for the pastry
cream the crimpier
175 g of sugar 45 g of allpurpose flour
or plain flour in England in Europe two
whole eggs 500 g of milk that has been
heated 100 g of cream 10 g of honey you
could also use glucose or invert sugar 5
g of butter 7 and 1 half grams of
vanilla extract and if you want to add a
vanilla bean seeds into that, then you
absolutely can. Finally, a pinch of salt
to balance that out. So, there we go.
Lot of stuff. See why I don't want to
make the brownies, too. Anyway, let's
get everything weighed out and start
making this burnt caramel. 50 g of sugar
and add a touch of water to it. You
don't need to add a huge amount of
water. You're just trying to make that
sugar kind of wet. It's going to be
burnt off anyway. So, with those now
combined, we can pour it into a pan.
Don't swirl it. Don't touch it with
anything. Don't stir it. We're going to
put it on the heat and we're going to
gently heat this up until we get to
quite a dark color. So, burnt caramel as
we're adding this to dairy is going to
lose a lot of the flavor. So, we're
going to burn it quite a bit. So, let's
get that going. Now, that's going on a
medium high setting. This is the stage
that we're going to bring it up to. The
temperature is almost irrelevant because
we are literally just giving it the
flavor. Temperature is much more
important for this kind of thing when
you're making actual caramels with the
inclusion of butter and cream. And
that's the stage where you need to be
careful as to where you cook it to.
That's the final cooking stage of your
sugar emulsion. In this situation, we
just need to bring it up to a high
temperature to burn it.
So, keeping an eye on our sugar, we're
going to get our milk and cream in here.
454 of milk, 330 of cream. Our water is
starting to evaporate off nicely. The
sugar syrup has started to thicken,
which means it's going to start browning
pretty quickly. Keep an eye on it. Don't
walk away. It will burn really quickly.
Although, we do want it to burn. So, how
much we want it to burn. That depends on
how much flavor you want. So, with that
in there, what we've got in here is we
got our skim milk powder, we got our
sugar, we got our guar. And we've got
our lein. I'm using soy lein in this.
Doesn't matter if you use sunflower
lein, liquid lein, that is fine. By
using less than on its own, not egg
yolks, we don't have to superheat this
base. We're just going to stir it to
dissolve the sugar. So, this is actually
a semi- cold process. Let's get these in
here and give these a nice stir. Caramel
is starting to brown now. So, I do need
to keep an eye on this. Stirring this
will dissolve the sugars in a couple of
minutes. So, everything should tally up
quite nicely. Then, we're browning
nicely. Now, adding cold caramel, no,
adding hot caramel to this cold base
would be an absolute nightmare. It would
just go rock solid. So, what we're going
to do is we're going to take
a little bit of our base and put that in
a container like so.
And we're going to pop this in a
microwave and heat this up. Our little
bit of base is heated up. A tiny whisk.
That's too tiny. This is going to spit.
We need 30 g of this into here. There we
go.
And then you can simply stir that back
together because that base is warm. That
will relquequify the caramel. So just
keep stirring and it will turn back to
liquid. If your caramel seizes up in
adding it to your dairy, don't stress
about it. You can just pop in the
microwave for 5second bursts. Uh heat
that all back up together while stirring
it and it will all come back to a nice
caramel dairy mix. Don't heat it for too
long. That sugar is already super hot.
If you go more than 5 seconds at a time,
the likelihood is it will boil over and
make an absolute mess of your microwave.
Ask me how I know. But we need to keep
stirring this for a little bit to cool
it back down. We don't want to add this
boiling hot sugar dairy mixture back
into all our dairy. It will just
solidify and then we'll have to heat the
whole thing back up. So, what we can
just do is just stir that for a few
minutes to bring that down to an
acceptable temperature. If again you
want to put this if you put this into
your dairy base and it solidifies and
turns into a solid block, don't stress
about it. Pop it on a hob for a few
minutes whilst gently heating it up.
Once you get to about 30 to 35 C, the
sugar will start to melt back down. You
can just stir it back together and it
will all incorporate nicely. Car adding
caramels to dairy bases, specifically
cold dairy bases, is quite difficult. So
doing a cold processed caramel ice
cream, it's not ideal. Right now we're
all completely mixed together. Let's
pour this into our base while stirring
it. Stir it well as you mix it back
together.
Nicely incorporated.
Nice burnt caramel smell coming out of
there. So, we're just going to keep
stirring this for a couple of minutes.
Make sure all of that is completely
reinccorporated. Caramel will just
dissolve in liquid. It It will just take
longer in a cold liquid than it would in
a hot liquid. So again, don't don't
stress if things go wrong. There's
always a way around it. There is our
burnt caramel ice cream base that can
now go in a container. We're going to
just let this chill down to fridge
temperatures. And we're doing that cuz
we've added that hot sugar. We've
brought the temperature up. We've added
we've added solids into this cold dairy.
So that's brought the temperature up. So
we're going to get this nice chilled
back down. You know, whatever your
fridge temperature is, usually 2 to 3
centrade. So that's what we're going to
do here. Uh, whilst that's chilling,
let's make the pastry cream or crimp it
to the air. Right, for the pastry cream,
let's get our milk and cream in here cuz
we're going to heat this up in the
microwave. So, 500 of milk, 100 of
cream. You can have the amount of pastry
cream here. I'm going to use this for
something else, but this will give you
five, six, 7, about 800 g worth of
pastry cream. Uh, if you don't want that
much, you you can just have it cuz that
would be more than enough for a 1 kilo
base. So, with that in there, we're
going to pop this in the microwave and
heat it up. We're going to get it quite
hot. Quite hot being about 85 centrade.
With that doing that, we're going to put
our sugar and our flour in here. So,
sugar, 175 g of sugar, 45 g of our
allpurpose flour, and we're going to
just mix that together. into our flour
and our sugar. We're going to add our
two eggs and stir all of that together
until it's all nicely combined and a
smooth paste.
Now our milk and cream is up to
temperature. We're going to start to
combine this with our
egg, sugar, and flour mixture. Just a
little bit at a time. If you dump it all
in, it will take you forever to combine
it back up. So just a little bit and
then you can start adding it a little
bit more as you go. So we're going to
pop this on heat and just a medium high
heat and keep stirring constantly and it
will start to thicken up nicely. So as
it comes up to that boiling point,
simmering point, it will really start to
thicken. That's that flour kicking in.
Pinch of salt. Stir that in. 5 g of
honey. In goes our vanilla. 7 1/2 g of
butter. It's 5 g. Stir that in. And you
can add uh vanilla bean if you want.
Scrape the seeds out, etc., etc. I'm
going to use vanilla bean
powder.
Now, we have our flan creme caramel
flavor here. This is where this is. So,
that caramel flavor from the the dessert
is in the base. This is our vanilla
custard flavor in here. All we need to
do now is put this into a container like
that.
And we're going to cover it with our
plastic wrap or cling film. But we're
going to cover that top. We're going to
put it straight on the surface. We don't
want a skin filming on this. to cool
down somewhat before we put it in the
fridge and then we can deal with
everything when it's ready. Right, let's
get the ice cream in and churning. We're
gonna get the brownies out of the
refrigerator/ freezer. I'm going to use
Costco two bite brownies. Um, use
whatever brownies you have available.
I'm going to do a brownie video soon, so
maybe try those. And we'll get our creme
peticier ready. So, ice cream in first.
[Music]
nice and quiet after having the work
done. Uh for those that follow along,
there was a vibratory issue caused
inside the machine. So, as the machine
vibrates, it caused the movement of some
of the electrical cables and then those
cables got pulled off eventually. It's
not really a manufacturing default, more
just a oneoff. So, uh I wouldn't really
worry about it. These machines a bit
like tanks. And our brownies. So, I'm
going to get these brownies chopped up.
And then once we dish up, we can start
spooning it all together.
Caramel ice creams are much easier made
when you do them in a more traditional
sense that you heat up the base, you
heat up the the caramel, you combine the
two, and then once it's all emulsified
together, you cool it down as normal.
That's the way to make caramel ice
creams. Not this way, which is cold
processed caramel. It's a pain, but I
wanted to show you that it can be done
anyway.
Um, yeah, doing cold processed caramel
ice cream is a is is a pain in the ass.
I'm not going to lie. You know, you're
taking cuz we're not adding I mean this
one anyway. Don't ask me why I wanted to
do it this way. I I don't know. Can't
can't tell you why. Um, sometimes I just
like to do things really the most
awkward way possible. And that's what it
is. Because in this caramel, we're not
taking, you know, cream and butter and
adding it in to create a softer caramel
texture and then adding that back into
the base. We are we're taking deeply
burnt caramel without the dairy or the
butter and adding that into the dairy
base. So having to heat that bit of base
up so that it would actually combine
it. It's doable. Yeah. I mean, I
probably wouldn't do it in the microwave
like I did it. I would take some of that
base out like I did. Put it in a small
pan, heat that up, then add that ultra
deep burnt caramel into that. Make sure
it's completely emulsified. So you got
to get that little bit of bass up really
high in temperature, you know, kind of
80 90 C and then add the whole lot back
into your base that way. It it obviously
worked cuz I've done it here, but I
wouldn't recommend it. Here we go. Now,
as you can see by the picture on screen
now,
the pastry cream crimpier
is visible and it's noticeable streaks
through. It's not super bright color cuz
you got it's basically the same color,
but it's scooped and it didn't separate
because obviously that's uh that pastry
cream has been balanced to suit the ice
cream.
I don't know whether I like it or not.
The burnt caramel flavor absolutely
comes through on this base. Much more
than I thought it would to be fair. So,
the the caramel ice cream is pretty
decent. Burnt caramel ice cream. That's
the flavor that you're getting. Maybe
it's just that I'm not a big fan of
burnt caramel ice cream. The cremeicier
is it's not separated, but it's not
super smooth either. And and I'm not
sure you'd be able to get that. It's
still kind of icy in the way that like a
raspberry ripple would be icy. The
brownies, like I said, these are Costco
two byite brownies. They've got this
kind of perfect freezing texture. And
Ghirardelli boxed brownies. Picture on
screen. These work perfectly in ice
cream, too. Don't overcook them. You
don't want cakey brownies in ice cream.
You want super fudgy brownies,
borderline uncooked. Anyway, it's nice
to get back to what this channel used to
do. And that's just something I want to
touch on before we close out this video
is for the last maybe 18 months. I cuz
this channel is just me. I I do all the
filming, all the editing, all the
making, everything. It's just me. Nobody
else helps me with this channel at all.
I for some reason
try to please a certain group of people
and I'm not doing that anymore. So,
we're just going to go back to what
Polar ice cream was always about, and
that is making
really good ice creams, luxury ice
creams at home. Things like Ben and
Jerry's and Hagenars, Jenny's, uh you
name it. All all the the big ice cream
companies. We're going to go back to
making all of their kind of flavors. So,
that is what this channel is going to
go. We're going to go back to roots. So,
if you've got an ice cream that is
purchasable in the stores, let me know
what it is and we'll make it. Thanks
very much for watching. Don't forget to
like and subscribe and I'll see you next
time when I have no idea what I'm going
to make. So, so if you want to suggest
something, go for it. You've got 3 days
and then I'll make it.